<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
  <!ENTITY GFDL  SYSTEM "fdl-appendix.xml">
  <!ENTITY app "Wallch">
  <!ENTITY application "<application>&app;</application>">
  <!ENTITY appversion "2.28">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "2.28">
]>
<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Template Maintained by the GNOME Documentation Project:
  http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp
  Template version: 2.0 beta
  Template last modified Feb 12, 2002
-->

<!-- =============Document Header ============================= -->
<article id="index" lang="en">
<!-- please do not change the id; for translations, change lang to -->
<!-- appropriate code -->

  <articleinfo>
    <title>&application; Manual</title>
    <abstract role="description">
      <para>
        &application; allows your Desktop Wallpaper to change automatically.
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <copyright>
      <year>2010-2012</year>
      <holder>Leon Vytanos (leon.check.me@gmail.com)</holder>
      <holder>Alex Solanos (alexsol.developer@gmail.com)</holder>
    </copyright>

  <!-- translators: uncomment this:

  <copyright>
   <year>2006</year>
   <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
  </copyright>

  -->

<!-- An address can be added to the publisher information.  If a role is
     not specified, the publisher/author is the same for all versions of the
     document.  -->
    <publisher role="maintainer">
      <publishername>Wallch Team</publishername>
<email>wallch.developers@gmail.com</email>
    </publisher>

   &legal;
   <!-- This file  contains link to license for the documentation (GNU FDL), and
        other legal stuff such as "NO WARRANTY" statement. Please do not change
        any of this. -->

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Leon</firstname>
        <surname>Vytanos</surname>
	<email>leon.check.me@gmail.com</email>
      </author>
      <author>
        <firstname>Alex</firstname>
        <surname>Solanos</surname>
	<email>alexsol.developer@gmail.com</email>
      </author>

<!-- This is appropriate place for other contributors: translators,
      maintainers,  etc. Commented out by default.
       <othercredit role="translator">
        <firstname>Latin</firstname>
        <surname>Translator 1</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>Latin Translation Team</orgname>
          <address> <email>translator@gnome.org</email> </address>
        </affiliation>
        <contrib>Latin translation</contrib>
      </othercredit>
-->
    </authorgroup>

   

    <legalnotice>
      <title>Feedback</title>
      <para>
        To report a bug regarding this application, you can report it 
    <ulink url="https://bugs.launchpad.net/wallpaper-changer" type="http">
    at launchpad</ulink>.
      </para>
<!-- Translators may also add here feedback address for translations -->
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <indexterm zone="index">
    <primary>&application;</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm zone="index">
    <primary>wallch</primary>
  </indexterm>

<!-- ============= Document Body ============================= -->
<!-- ============= Introduction ============================== -->
<section id="intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <!-- manrevision 2.0 compatibility -->
  <anchor id="aboutex"/>
  <anchor id="notice"/>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>&application;</primary>
    <secondary>Manual</secondary>
    <tertiary>wallch</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
  &app; is a General purpose Wallpaper Changer for the GNOME and UNITY desktop which can change the desktop background image after an adjustable time and many more. The aim of &app; is to make it easier for you to keep your desktop "fresh" and new!
  </para>

</section>
<sect1 id="getting-started"> 
    <title>Getting Started</title> 

    <sect2 id="start">
      <title>To Start <application>&app;</application></title>

<orderedlist>
    <listitem id="bs4u1a6">
     <para>Start Wallch.</para>
     <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
       <colspec colwidth="1.219*" colname="1" colnum="1"/>
       <colspec colwidth="4.188*" colname="2" colnum="2"/>
       <tbody valign="top">
        <row id="bsptywf">
         <entry colname="1">
          <para>GNOME:</para>
         </entry>
         <entry colname="2">
          <para>Click Applications &gt; Accessories &gt; &app; Wallpaper Changer.</para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row id="bsptywg">
         <entry colname="1">
          <para>UNITY:</para>
         </entry>
         <entry colname="2">
          <para>Press the Super Key, search for "wallch" and click it.</para>
         </entry>
        </row>
        <row id="bsptywh">
         <entry colname="1">
          <para>Command Line:</para>
         </entry>
         <entry colname="2">
          <para>Enter <command>wallch</command> and press Return.</para>
         </entry>
        </row>
       </tbody>
      </tgroup>
     </informaltable>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="when-start">
      <title>When You Start <application>&app;</application></title>
      <para>When you start <application>&app;</application>, the following window is displayed.</para>

      <!-- ==== Figure ==== -->
      <figure id="start-fig"> 
	<title><application>&app;</application> Start Up Window</title> 
	<screenshot> 
	  <mediaobject> 
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="figures/wallch.jpg" format="JPG"/> 
	    </imageobject>
	    <textobject> 
	      <phrase>Shows <application>&app;</application> main window with
		  sidebar opened on playlist. Contains
		  menubar, display area, sidebar, elapsed time slider, seek control
		  buttons, volume slider and statusbar.
          </phrase>
	    </textobject> 
	  </mediaobject> 
	</screenshot> 
      </figure>
      <!-- ==== End of Figure ==== -->

      <!-- Include any descriptions of the GUI immediately after the screenshot of the main UI, -->
      <!-- for example, the items on the menubar and on the toolbar. This section is optional. -->
      <para>The <application>&app;</application> window contains the following elements:
      </para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
          <term><interface>Menubar</interface></term>

          <listitem>
            <para><variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                  <term><guimenu>File</guimenu></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Use this menu to add files like a &app; album, single images or a folder with it's subfolers; to start, pause or stop the process; to move to the next image  
                 or to quit the application.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                  <term><guimenu>Edit</guimenu></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Use this menu to download the extra 1000 wallpapers, view your History logs, set your Preferences, find an image in the list and use some extra functionalities.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>


                <varlistentry>
                  <term><guimenu>Help</guimenu></term>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>View information about &app; through the
                    <guimenuitem>About</guimenuitem> menuitem. Open this
                    document with the <guimenuitem>Contents</guimenuitem>
                    menuitem or by pressing <keycap>F1</keycap>, view Statistics about the application, check for updates, donate, ask a question or report a bug.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
              </variablelist></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><interface>Item's List.</interface></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The item's list is the images that &app; will use to change the Desktop Background. This list is usable when you have normally select images from your hard disk and start the process and also when you have enabled the Folder Monitoring from the Extras dialog. In the latter occasion, the list will show the images that are on the monitored folders. Use the buttons right of it to add and remove images (if Folder Monitoring is not enabled) or change their position on the list. You can also add pictures and &app; albums by drag-and-droppping them into the list.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>


        <varlistentry>
          <term><interface>Preview of item.</interface></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>When you select an image on the Item's List a preview of the image will be available.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term><interface>Time.</interface></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The time interval for the wallpaper changing mode. This will show the time needed for the next image to change, both in the normal wallpaper changing process and in live earth wallpaper process.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term><interface>Random images/time.</interface></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>These two checkboxes enable you to a) change Desktop Background by picking randomly images from the list and b) change images in a random time (20 min max).
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><interface>Seek control buttons.</interface></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The seek control buttons enable you to move to the next image and to Start/Pause/Stop the current process.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><interface>Take Screenshot.</interface></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Take a screenshot of the entire screen.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><interface>Take Webcam Image.</interface></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Take a picture from your web camera.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

	
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

<section id="using">
  <title>Usage</title>

<term><interface>The usage is rather simple:</interface></term>
<para>1. Add your wallpapers to the Item's List by simply drag-and-dropping them to the List or by clicking the Add button to add images ( Ctrl + I ), or by clicking the Add Folder Button to add images that are in a folder with it's subfolders ( Ctrl + D ), or by adding a &app; album by dragging and dropping it at the List or from <menuchoice>
		<guisubmenu>File</guisubmenu>
		<guimenuitem>Add</guimenuitem>
                <guimenuitem>Add a &app; album</guimenuitem>
	      </menuchoice>. ( Ctrl + O ). </para>
<para>2. Set the interval of the wallpaper changing mode via the slider.</para>
<para>3. Press “Start” to start the process. That’s it.</para>
    <note>

      <para>
        One thing that you have to take note is that once you “Start” the program, you won’t be able to add/remove wallpapers anymore. You will have to “Stop” the application to make changes to the list. Also, the above description of the usage does not apply for picture of the day or live earth wallpaper.
      </para>
    </note>
<note>
      <para>
        You can also change Desktop Wallpaper choosing images randomly or in a random time if the respective checkboxes are checked.
      </para>
    </note>
<note>
      <para>
        You can also right click on an item on the List to a) Set It as a Desktop Background ( Alternative: Double Click it or select it and press <keycap>Return</keycap> ), b) remove non-existent items that are on the list but not in your hard drive, d) permanently delete image from hard drive, e) open image's location, f) copy image's path, g) copy image itself to clipboard (to paste it at Gimp for example), h) rotate the image or i) view the image's properties.
      </para>
    </note>
<para></para>
<term><interface>Controlling &app; from the tray (not recommended for Unity)</interface></term>
      <para>
When &app; is minimized to the tray, right-clicking the icon in the tray will reveal a menu in which you will have a 'Show' action which will restore &app;, all seeking buttons and some options like showing the preferences dialog, the about dialog and closing &app;. Note that users that use Unity will be able to use this feature, but it will be more usable for other users, because in the Unity environment, functions such as 'one click to change wallpaper' from the tray don't work, conversely with users of other environments.
      </para>


<note>
      <para>
        If the wallpaper changing mode is running just click on the tray icon and it will proceed to the next image (not working for Unity users). If the wallpaper changing module is not running it will just restore the app. Also middle-click to close &app; instantly.
      </para>
    </note>
</section>

 <section id="prefs">
    <title>Preferences</title>
    <para>To modify the preferences of <application>&app;</application>, choose
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.</para>

    <sect2 id="startup">
      <title>Startup</title>
      <variablelist>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Change Wallpapers on Pc-Start up</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
	      	<para><guilabel>Change Desktop Wallpaper (Once)</guilabel>: On Pc Start-up, &app; will change once the current Desktop Wallpaper by picking randomly an image from the last Items' List. Alternatively, if Folder Monitoring is enabled, then &app; will load the pictures of the monitored folders and will pick a random image from there. If no images are available, then an error message will appear.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>Start changing Desktop Wallpapers</guilabel>: On Pc Start-up, &app; will start the wallpaper changing module by picking randomly images from the last Item's List. Alternatively, if Folder Monitoring is enabled, then &app; will load the pictures of the monitored folders and will start changing wallpapers, picking randomly images from there. If no images are available, then an error message will appear. The time interval will be the last used.
	        </para>
              </listitem>

	          <listitem>
				<para><guilabel>Auto-enable Live Earth Wallpaper</guilabel>: On Pc Start-up, Live Earth Wallpaper will be automatically activated changing your wallpaper every 30 min.
                </para>
              </listitem>

	          <listitem>
				<para><guilabel>Auto-enable Picture Of The Day</guilabel>: On Pc Start-up, Picture Of The Day will be automatically activated. Picture of the day is a feature provided by wikipedians. It is an image that changes once every day provided here: <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Picture_of_the_day" type="http">Wikipedia - Picture Of The Day</ulink>. &app; takes care of everything and changes your wallpaper once a day according to the corresponding picture of the day provided by wikipedians. This picture is of general interest, containing usually content such as beautiful images of nature, famous persons etc. Also, images can be quite large sometimes, up to 10 MB (rarely). The image updates around 00:30 UTC, so &app; will check around this time (or after this time, if PC is e.g. turned off then) to download and change this image. Internet connection is of vital importance.
                </para>
              </listitem>

            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>	
        </variablelist>
        </sect2>

    <sect2 id="general">
      <title>General</title>
      <variablelist>
<varlistentry>
	  <term>Minimize to tray</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Select it if you want &app; to be minimized to tray (not recommended for Unity users).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>	

<varlistentry>
	  <term>Hide app when 'Start' is pressed</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>&app; will automatically hide if you have selected this option and then you press the 'Start' button. Wallch will go completely to the background and you will be able to recover it by starting it again, unless you have chosen to minimize to tray, which is what it will do if you have selected this option and the you press the 'Start' button.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>	

<varlistentry>
	  <term>Unity progressbar</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>&app;, if attached to the unity launcher, will display a progressbar in &app;'s icon, similar to the progressbar right from the Items' List. This progressbar will be visible only when application is hidden (minimized to tray or completely running on the background).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>	

<varlistentry>
	  <term>Rotate images on add</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Every image added on &app; will be checked for Exif data. This option is recommended only if you have a camera that saves Exif data in the images so as to reveal the orientation of the picture taken. It is notable that this will alter the added images by really rotating them! Also, it should be mentioned that the program may become a little bit slower, especially if a huge amount of images are added to the program and need to be rotated.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>	

<varlistentry>
	  <term>Style</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>You can tell &app; how to display your wallpaper by selecting the 'Style' to display. Tile will tile the wallpaper to fill up the screen, this is useful for small wallpapers that would otherwise look distorted when zoomed in. Zoom fills up the screen like a magnifying glass. Center will center the wallpaper to the center of your screen. Scale will strech out the wallpaper to fill your screen, but will not change the aspect ratio, so that the wallpaper will fill up your screen the best it can, without modifying the picture itself.  And finally, you can use stretch and span for multimonitor screens.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>	

<varlistentry>
	  <term>Language</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Change the language of the program.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>	

<varlistentry>
	  <term>History</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>&app; can keep history logs of the time and the options of the changed wallpaper. You can view History logs from
        <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>History</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>	



      </variablelist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="notifications">
      <title>Notifications</title>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>&app; provides also a desktop and/or sound notification when a wallpaper changes. You can select your own sound to be played for the sound notification function. 
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>
</section>

<section id="extras">
    <title>Extras</title>
    <para>To view the extras dialog choose
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Extras</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.</para>

<sect2 id="live earth">
      <title>Live Earth Wallpaper</title>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>One interesting thing about &app; is the ability to set Live Earth images as the desktop wallpaper. Just press the “Activate Live Earth Wallpaper” button and your desktop wallpaper will be updated once every 30 mins with the current image of earth.
            </para>

    <note>

      <para>
        
Live Earth Wallpaper module can’t work concurrently with the main wallpaper changing module. If you have “Started” the wallpaper changing module, you won’t be able to activate the Live Earth Wallpaper and vice versa. In addition, the changing interval is set to 30 mins and this cannot change.

      </para>
    </note>

          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

<sect2 id="foldermonitor">
      <title>Folder Monitoring</title>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Monitor a folder or more for new or deleted images, and proceed to the corresponding actions to the Items' List.
            </para>

    <note>

      <para>
This feature enables you to monitor a folder or more for new images. Any new images added to the folder(s) will be automatically added to the list of the images. Also, if an image is deleted from the folder, it will also be removed from the list. Also these actions can be done concurrently, while the process is running, without any problem. Also, note that folder monitoring can work with the Start-up options.

      </para>
    </note>

          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>
<sect2 id="pictureofday">
      <title>Picture Of the day</title>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Picture of the day is a feature that enables you to have a new interesting image as desktop background every day.
            </para>

    <note>

      <para>
If this is enabled, then &app; will download once a day an image chosen by wikipedians (<ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Picture_of_the_day" type="http">Wikipedia - Picture Of The Day</ulink>), around at 00:30 UTC or later (if PC is turned off that time). Please note that images can be quite large, but &app; will provide only images with size max to 10 MB, resizing the ones exceeding this limit. This picture is of general interest, containing usually content such as beautiful images of nature, famous persons etc. Internet connection is of vital importance. If you want picture of the day to run concurrently every day, you will have to enable it from the Preferences dialog, under the 'Startup' section.

      </para>
    </note>

          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

<sect2 id="helpus">
      <title>Help if you want</title>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Aliens are invading Earth!
            </para>

    <note>

      <para>
You can help us by translating the application to your language, if it hasn't been translated yet. Also, angry aliens are invading Earth. Scientists found out that they become calm when being fed with money. We need your help to save the planet! Donate by clicking on <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Help</guisubmenu>
		<guimenuitem>Donate</guimenuitem></menuchoice> if you want via paypal.

      </para>
    </note>

          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>




  </section>


<section id="about">
  <title>About</title>
  <para>
    &app; was written ( In random order ) by Alex Solanos <email>alexsol.developer@gmail.com</email>.
    and Leon Vytanos <email>leon.check.me@gmail.com</email>.
    To find more information about &app;, please visit the
    <ulink url="http://wallch.t35.com" type="http">
    &app; website</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para>
    To report a bug regarding this application, you can report it 
    <ulink url="https://bugs.launchpad.net/wallpaper-changer" type="http">
    at launchpad</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para>This program is distributed under the terms of the GNU
    General Public license as published by the Free Software
    Foundation; either version 3 of the License, or (at your option)
    any later version. A copy of this license can be found at the
    <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html" type="http">GNU site</ulink>, or in the file
    COPYING included with the source code of this program.
  </para>
</section>

</article>
